<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mobile | Benedict Chan]]></title>
  <link href="http://benedict-chan.github.io/blog/categories/mobile/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://benedict-chan.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-06T10:51:49+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://benedict-chan.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Benedict Chan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to authenticate from a mobile application to an existing web application]]></title>
    <link href="http://benedict-chan.github.io/blog/2014/02/05/how-to-authenticate-from-a-mobile-application-to-an-existing-web-application/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-05T16:35:51+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://benedict-chan.github.io/blog/2014/02/05/how-to-authenticate-from-a-mobile-application-to-an-existing-web-application</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The problem</h2>

<p>The experience for a user authenticating to a web site vs a mobile application is totally different.</p>

<h3>The web experience</h3>

<ol>
<li>User comes to a web site</li>
<li>User got redirected to the Login Page if needed</li>
<li>User login by using their UserId,Password (cookie is created)</li>
<li>User logout or leave the browser (cookie may expire)</li>
<li>User come to the web applicaton next time, may need to login again (if cookie expired)</li>
</ol>


<h3>The mobile app experience</h3>

<ol>
<li>User open the app for the first time, asked login with their UserId,Password</li>
<li>After that, in most cases, user access to the app assuming they are always logged in and never need to logout or login again.</li>
</ol>


<h2>The solution</h2>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Create an API for the mobile to authenticate an user</h3>

<p>An API call is needed for the mobile app to authenticate an user by UserId/password.
For security reason, it should connect via a SSL secure connection.</p>

<h3>Issue a token to the mobile from the API when the user logins successfully</h3>

<p>For security reason, we should never save a user password in the mobile app, therefore, what we do is to issue a token which acts like a never expired cookie as in a web application.</p>

<h4>About the token</h4>

<p>When creating this authentication token, we should remember that a user may have more than one device installing our mobile application.
Therefore
1. The relationship for a user to a token is not a one-to-one but one-to-many relationship.
2. The token should have a corresponding timestamp when created because in case a user changed their password, all token issued before this password changing time should be expired</p>

<h3>Calling other Web Application&rsquo;s API</h3>

<p>Your mobile application should now use this token to call your server-side APIs. Your server-side should validate this token as a similair way as how to validates a login cookie.
One way to pass this token, is to send it throught HTTP headers instead of a URL query parameters.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
